<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An epistle general containing wholsome exhortations and good counsel from the spirit of truth unto all such as are or may be under the judgment or sentence of banishment, for the testimony of Jesus Christ ... / by ... W.B.</title>
            <author>Bayly, William, d. 1675.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1664</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27125</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1524</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16452</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12164712</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12164712</idno>
            <idno type="VID">55272</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A27125)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 55272)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 857:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An epistle general containing wholsome exhortations and good counsel from the spirit of truth unto all such as are or may be under the judgment or sentence of banishment, for the testimony of Jesus Christ ... / by ... W.B.</title>
                  <author>Bayly, William, d. 1675.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to William Bayly. cf. BM.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines.</term>
               <term>Judgment.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:55272:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN EPISTLE GENERAL CONTAINING Wholſome <hi>Exhortations</hi> and <hi>Good Counſel</hi> from the <hi>Spirit of Truth,</hi> unto all <hi>ſuch</hi> as are or may be under the <hi>Judgment</hi> or <hi>Sentence</hi> OF BANISHMENT, FOR THE <hi>Teſtimony</hi> of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> (which is <hi>held</hi> in a <hi>Tender Conſcience</hi>) through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Nation of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As alſo, Unto all them that are yet at <hi>Liberty</hi> (to be <hi>faithful</hi> to the Lord, and meet <hi>often</hi> together in the fear of his <hi>Name,</hi> and not to <hi>fear Man,</hi> that ſhall be made as <hi>Graſs</hi>) and to all in <hi>Bonds, Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> and <hi>Holes</hi> every-where throughout the <hi>World,</hi> who are bearing (and ſuffering for) the ſame <hi>Teſtimony</hi> of <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> which the Lord hath <hi>decreed</hi> ſhall <hi>proſper</hi> and <hi>ſpread</hi> over all the <hi>World,</hi> till the <hi>Kingdoms</hi> thereof are become his <hi>Kingdoms,</hi> and he ſhall <hi>Reign</hi> for ever and ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With a few <hi>Words</hi> of <hi>Advice,</hi> to all who have or may have any <hi>Meſſage</hi> or <hi>Buſineſs</hi> upon the account of <hi>Truth</hi> to ſuch as are in <hi>Authority</hi> in the <hi>Nations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By a Servant of the Churches of Chriſt Jeſus. <hi>W. B.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1664.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:55272:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:55272:2"/>
            <head>AN EPISTLE GENERAL, Containing Wholſome <hi>Exhortations</hi> and <hi>Good Counſel,</hi> from the <hi>Spirit of Truth,</hi> unto all ſuch as are, or may be, under the <hi>Judgement</hi> or <hi>Sentence</hi> of <hi>BANISHMENT,</hi> for the <hi>Teſtimony</hi> of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>MY dear Friends and Brethren, who for your teſtimony of truth (and obedience to the God of <hi>Abraham</hi>) are or may be cauſed to wander (as ſome of our Fathers have done) from your Native Countries, and to be expoſed to the want of a certain dwelling place in the Earth, and to forſake All for the Name of Chriſt, that is neer and dear in the World, and be liable to great Jeopardies and Perils by Sea and Land, among Strangers, and in ſtrange Countries; why, take ye no thought for your Life, what ye ſhall eat, or what ye ſhall drink, or wherewith ye ſhall be clothed, or, for your Relations and Families, what they ſhall do in your Abſence, for the Lord (for whoſe ſake ye ſuffer) will provide both for you and them, as ye faithful to him abide, whoſe tender bowells of compaſſions are open toward them that fear him, and pittieth them, even as a Father pittieth his Children. But conſider how great and weighty a Work and Service the Lord at this time hath called you unto, and how great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly the Honour and Glory of his holy Name is concerned therein; the Lord my God give you a clear underſtanding thereof, and direct you in his Counſel in all ye take in hand, that in it ye may ſtand faithful, and be preſerved in his pure Fear, in meekneſs and wiſdom, to his praiſe; for it is the faithfulneſs of his people, in their patient ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and circumſpect, humble, ſobe, juſt, wiſe, upright, harmleſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, that will anſwer the Principle of God in all Nations, and preach his Kingdom come nigh unto People, among whom-ſoever
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:55272:3"/>they may come, or be ſcattered for his Name-ſake; and by this Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel (which is everlaſting) ſhall thouſands be converted unto God, and multitudes be gathered into his Name, and many through his knowledge ſhall be juſtified, which muſt cover the Earth as the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters cover the Sea, as was propheſied in dayes paſt.</p>
            <p>Therefore my dear Friends, be ye not at all diſcouraged in your ſufferings, but look at the End for which the Lord hath called you thereunto, which is the exaltation of his Name, and the gathering of his pretious Seed out of Captivity, where they have been ſcattered in all quarters, in the cloudy and dark day, that they might come to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit reſt in their own Land, and partake of the glory which was before the world was: and <hi>conſult not</hi> with fleſh and blood in any thing, for ye have need of <hi>great watchfulneſs</hi> this day, that no reaſoner may enter you, to the betraying the <hi>Innocent</hi> into the Sinners hands, ſo that Spirit will ſell the Lord that bought them, to ſave ſelf and the things of this Life: But fleſh and blood muſt not inherit the Kingdom of God, for 'tis prepared for that bleſſed innocent Seed only, which hath no Kingdom in this World, out is a ſtranger in the Earth, So let your pure breathings be manifeſt unto the Lord, that ye may receive power from him, be preſerved in his truth, out of all the ſnares of this World, and commit your cauſe and all ye have, freely and wholly unto him, and be purely reſigned and ſubject to his heavenly Will (eying his Glory) in all things, at all times, and in all places; for the Work is his, and the Cauſe ye are engaged in is the Lords, and not your own; ye are but as Servants or Inſtruments in this great Work, which the Lord hath begun, and is cauſing to ſpread and proſper throughout the Earth, that he may get himſelf a <hi>great,</hi> and <hi>glorious,</hi> and <hi>dreadful Name,</hi> to the ends of the <hi>World,</hi> who ſhall be made to bow down and worſhip at his foot-ſtool, and confeſs that we are his People, and that the Everlaſting God is with us, is on our ſide, and ſights for us, who cannot ſtrive, nor fight for our ſelves, nor avenge our own cauſe, but leave it to him who judgeth righteouſly; and this ſhall be an evident token that our Kingdom is not of this World unto all people.</p>
            <p>Therefore my dear Friends and Brethren, faint not in your minds, neither be ye diſcouraged as concerning the greatneſs of the Trials ye have to undergo, but caſt your burthen (in this matter) upon the Lord, for the weight of your ſufferings herein he hath pondred, and it's come near unto him, and to the hearts of his dear Children, whoſe ſecret Cries and tender Breathings are unceſſantly poured forth into his boſome, in your behalf, in the tender yearning bowels of his everlaſting
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:55272:3"/>compaſſions; that ye may ſtand <hi>faithful</hi> in his counſel, and ſo walk, that his glorious <hi>Name</hi> may be <hi>exalted,</hi> and his <hi>Truth glorified in you,</hi> and <hi>by you,</hi> and by <hi>all</hi> that make mention thereof; elſe to what end is all our ſufferings and profeſſion of his Name in the World? <hi>Surely, ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> the Lord is chuſing a <hi>Remnant</hi> to himſelf (to walk with him in faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulneſes) that ſhall greatly honour him, and magnifie, and reverence his <hi>Holy Name,</hi> and bring praiſe unto him in this his day, and ſuch only will the Lord my God honour with everlaſting dominion, and beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie with his Eternal Salvation and Peace. Oh happy is the man, and happy will be that ſoul, whoſe lot falls in this ground; and verily its but a little while, and he will wipe away the reproach of this his cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen Remnant, and plead their cauſe with all their Oppreſſors, when the meaſures of the iniquities of his Adverſaries are filled up, and our Faith and Patience ſufficiently tried, and proved, and made manifeſt to the World; for of this great controverſie (now in hand) the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Seed of God is very ſenſible through Nations, which gives many People to ſee and diſcern, an abſolute difference of Spirit, and a great gulf fixed between us and our adverſaries; and this ſhall ariſe and break the hearts of thouſands, who are yet afar off, when they ſhall hear of your patient innocent ſufferings, only for your tender Conſcience and the Worſhip of your God, to whoſe Name and Power many ſhall confeſs (as the King in <hi>Daniels</hi> day) that he is the <hi>Living God, and ſtedfaſt for ever, and his Kingdom that which ſhall never be deſtroyed, and his Dominion ſhall be even to the end; he delivereth and reſcueth, and he worketh ſigns and wonders in Heaven and in Earth.</hi> And thus is our God (who is the ſame) doing at this very day (though the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly ſee it not) as ſhall hereafter be confeſſed and publiſhed, as this was after the beloved <hi>Daniel</hi> was <hi>tried</hi> and <hi>proved,</hi> and not before, <hi>mark that;</hi> and then woe will be to your Perſecutors (as it was to his) when the Seed ſhall ariſe in the Nations and witneſs for you, and againſt them, who ſhall curſe the hour in which they were born, and the moment in which they breathed in the World, and the womb that bare them, that ever they ſhould be ſo blind to bring ſwift deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon their own heads, for the lucre of a moment of pleaſures.</p>
            <p>Therefore my dear Friends, let your minds be ſtayed, and your hearts fixed on the Lord, that ye may be alwayes kept and preſerved in the pure ſence of the weight and ponderouſneſs of this his great and honourable Work, which he hath called you into, that ſo ye may be patterns, and pure examples, of righteouſneſs, gravity, truth and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the Nations, even as Lights in a dark place, and as a City ſet
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:55272:4"/>on the Everlaſting Hill of God, above all the fury and rage of your ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, or their moſt ſubtilleſt Temptations or provocations, which ye may meet withall in your Travails and dayly exerciſes: From which my God deliver you, and keep you ſtedfaſt in watchfulneſs, wiſdome, and fear to the end; that ye may be preſerved out of all the ſnares of the Enemy, to the honour of his great Name, and the comfort and peace of your own ſouls; for its the endurer to the end, that ſhall be ſaved.</p>
            <p>And dear Friends, Take heed and beware of letting in the ſpirit of this world into your hearts, which naturally draws from God, into its own Center, to look after the riches, eaſe, and glory thereof; for it was not in vaine, that the ſame Spirit that now dwels in his Children, exhorted his Diſciples (in Ages paſt) to take heed and beware of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs, for a mans life conſiſteth not in the abundance of the things of this world which he may poſſeſs; For whoſoever ſhall let forth his mind after theſe things, and imbrace and entertain thoſe ſubtill Contrivances which may ariſe in the mind as Temptations, and ſhall follow the whiſperings thereof, and ſo let that be his Guide which leads to ſeek ſelf, <hi>his own honour, riches</hi> and <hi>glory,</hi> and not the things of Jeſus Chriſt, the Truth and its <hi>glory only, ſuch a one will be deſtroyed,</hi> and not preſerved. And this I have received from my God, to warne you of it, in tender love to your ſouls, and to the honour of his everlaſting Name, which muſt and will be exalted over all the Earth: And though a Thouſand ſhould fall on the right hand, and ten Thouſands on the left hand, yet the Lord ſhall be glorified, and all people be left without juſt excuſe.</p>
            <p>So the Lord God of Heaven direct you, and preſerve you chaſt and ſingle unto himſelf, for his Name ſake, and for his tender Seeds ſake, which is very dear and precious to him in every Nation. And this is the breathings of my heart and ſoul for you all, in the true and living ſenſe of the marvellous work and wonderfull things he is bringing to paſſe in theſe latter dayes; for its the Life muſt confound <hi>Babel,</hi> (as in the dayes of old) and build up <hi>Zion,</hi> whoſe walls is ſalvation and gives praiſes for evermore. Therefore in the retired watchfull, pure, light and life of God it ſelf, all dwell, alwayes eying his eternal power, and preſence to go before you (this was <hi>Moſes's</hi> mind, <hi>Carry us not hence except thy preſence go with us</hi>) for that is it by which the Lord wrought wonderfull things, and preſerved his people in all ages, who were obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient thereinto; and this hath preſerved us, who hath been led and guided thereby to this day, and will preſerve us to the end, as we are
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:55272:4"/>faithfull to obey its requirings, and no otherwayes can any be preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, or ſaved out of Temptations, and from the wrath to come. And this I do <hi>affirme</hi> from <hi>certain experience;</hi> For Tranſgreſſion againſt Gods requirings, was, and is, the Ground and cauſe of the ſeparation and alienation from him, and from his Covenant of promiſe, and is the breach of the peace and unity between God and man; So that there is no peace to the wicked, neither can there, ſo long as the whoredomes and witchcrafts of <hi>Jezabel</hi> remains, and diſobedience is as the ſin of witchcraft, and ſtubbornneſs is Iniquity and Idolatry; ſo that none can enjoy perfect peace with the holy God, but them whoſe feet are guid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by his light and <hi>holy Spirit,</hi> in the <hi>way</hi> of <hi>peace,</hi> which all the world that lye in wickedneſs (in Tranſgreſſion) are ignorant of, the way of peace they know not; But the Children of the Lord ſhall be all <hi>Taught</hi> of him, and great ſhall be the peace of his Children.</p>
            <p>So my dear Friends, mind the Light of the Lord, and let it be your Guide and Teacher, and your dwelling place; for them of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that are ſaved, muſt walke in the Light; mark, though they are ſaved, yet they muſt ſtill walke in the Light of the Holy City; and to it ſhall the gathering of the people be, who ſhall ſtock thereunto, as the doves to the windowes, as was propheſied and is now fullfiling in this our day, bleſſed for ever be the Name of the Lord. And take good heed to your Wayes, Words, and Carriages, amongſt all people where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever you come, as ye love the honour of God, and the peace of your own ſoules, in whoſe <hi>Name,</hi> in bowells of love, I lay it upon you all; for many will be the eyes; that will be ſharply fixed upon you, both for good and for evil, even to mark all your ſteps in every path which you ſhall tread with your feet: Therefore keep your feet in the way of peace, and walk with God, as <hi>Enoch,</hi> that ye may be more and more tranſlated, and taken up out of the ſight of all that watch for your halt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; ſo ſhall ye have the Witneſs in your ſelves, that your Wayes pleaſe the Lord, as he had, and as many of his dear children have at this day, with whom ye will have pretious Unity, as ye walk in the ſame ſteps, and mind the ſame things, that are eternal. And walk in low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, in the fear of God, and in love and tenderneſs one towards ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that men ſeeing your good Works, &amp; blameleſs converſation, may glorifie the Name of our God (in whoſe ſight, the ornament of a meek and quiet ſpirit is of great price) ſo ſhall your good and ſweet ſavour of all vertues abound and ſpread through Nations, And by theſe things (as leaves and fruits of the Tree of life) muſt the Nations be healed and replanted. And this is Gods decree and determination, and the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:55272:5"/>work he hath begun amongſt us, and is about at this very day, even to make new Heavens, and a new Earth, wherein Righteouſneſs ſhall dwell for ever; and the old ſhall paſs and is paſſing away with this great noiſe; for the Lord is finiſhing tranſgreſſion, and making an end of ſin, and bringing in everlaſting Righteouſneſs. Bleſſed is the eye that ſeeth and the heart that beleiveth and underſtandeth, and waiteth pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently and faithfully for the accompliſhment thereof, for ſuch only ſhall be kept under the ſhadow of the Almighty, who abide in the ſecret of the Moſt High, where they enjoy the ſure mercies of <hi>David,</hi> and the Kingdome and Dominion which never ends: Into which the God of Life bring you by his Eternal Power, and keep and preſerve you in his pure peaceable Wiſdom, at all times and in all places, where-ever you come, by Sea and Land. The Eternal God of my Life, of Heaven and Earth, be with you, and cauſe you to grow daily, as living plants to his renown and glory, and give you favour among all people, that gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations to come, may call you the bleſſed of the Lord. And as in this ye walk and abide, your enemies ſhall be made to confeſſe, that you are his choſen people, and many ſhall take hold of your skirts, becauſe of theſe venues, of which your garments will ſend forth a ſweet ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour among them But wo to that <hi>man,</hi> by whom the Lord ſhall be <hi>diſhonoured</hi> among you, it had been good for him, that he had not been born.</p>
            <p>So my dear friends and Brethren, dwell in your particular mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the grace of God, the light and power of his eternall Spirit of Truth, for whoſe Name ſake ye ſuffer, and reſign up your own wills (in the Croſſe daily) to his heavenly will and providence, and caſt all your care upon him, for he careth for his Children; only let this be your care, that his Name and Truth be kept clean, and not be reproached or blaſphemed, or ſuffer juſtly any way through any of you, for that would bring weakneſs, and even a Conſumption upon you, Condemnation and Anguiſh upon every ſoul that doth evil. So the eternal God keep your minds and hearts, in the deep Conſideration of the ſubſtance of theſe things: For truly Friends, great is the Lord, and greatly to be feared, and honoured, by all that make mention of his Name; the weight of which my ſoul doth daily ponder, and yet there remains a depth beyond that the mind of man can fathom. So un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord and his faithfull Witneſs I leave you, being cleare of what lay on me to write unto you in this matter at preſent, yet my ſoul doth daily travaile, and breath to my God for you all; For the honour of his Name is ſetled in my heart, daily more and more, in the ſence
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:55272:5"/>whereof I cannot forget his dear ſuffering people, who ſuffer ſo this Name-ſake. So the God of Heaven be with you, and his pure lively preſence fill your hearts with everlaſting joy and peace, and in this we ſhall daily meet together, and embrace each other, where nothing can ſeparate, as in it we faithfull abide, though we may be ſeparated as to the outward veſſells, through the wills of men, never to ſee each others faces more: the will of the Lord be done, ſaith my ſoul,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Who am your dear Brother in the bond of love and peace, which never changeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>ANd all friends every where, who are yet at liberty, keep your meetings together, in the Name and fear of the Lord, and be not daunted, or terrified, in any thing, as from your Adverſaries; for the Lord hath permitted or ſuffered them, in ſome meaſure, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their hearts deſire, to try you, and to ſift and winnow you for a ſeaſon, and ye ſhall have Tribulation ten dayes; For the Devil (who hath already caſt many of you into priſons) hath deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to winnow you as wheat, and not only ſo, but to deſtroy you utterly, root and branch from off the earth: But bleſſed be the Lord, who hath ſent down the Angel of his preſence, with the great Chain in his hand, and hath laid hold on the Dragon, ſo that he is limited (as in the dayes of <hi>Job</hi>) though he caſt out his floods of rage, and fury, againſt the man-child, perſecuting the Woman that brings him forth, and makes war with the remnant of her ſeed, which keep the Commandements, and hold faſt the Teſtimony of Jeſus. But his time is but ſhort, of which he is ſenſible, that his ruine and down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall approacheth, and dreadfulneſs hath taken hold of his heart, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the two Witneſſes are riſen (which torments the Earth) the Spirit of life from God is entered into them, and they ſtand upon their feet, and great fear is fallen upon their enemies, and this is the ſmoak of their Torment, of the fire which is kindled in their bowells, which will never be quenched, till the ungodly are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, whoſe ſwift deſtruction is haſtening upon them, and this way it cometh to paſſe, even by thoſe very actions and contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances by which he thinks to ſtand and uphold his power and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, ſo blind is your Adverſary, and his followers; and when they ſhall cry peace and ſafety, then ſhall ſudden deſtruction come up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, as pangs on a Woman in Travell, and they ſhall not eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:55272:6"/>
Therefore my dear Friends, be of good courage, and ſtand vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant for the Truth upon Earth, and dwell in the will of God, and be faithful to him in whatſoever he makes manifeſt to you, that ye may witneſs perfect peace with him, in all ye do or ſuffer for his Name ſake. And fear not him that can but kill the body, and hath power to do no more, but fear and reverence the living God of Heaven and Earth, and let him be your dread (and not man) and commit your ſelves, and all ye have, and the Cauſe ye are engaged in, freely unto the Lord, who takes care for his Children, that not one hair of their head ſhall periſh beyond his permiſſion; And keep your meetings diligently, and let in no Reaſoner or Conſulter with fleſh and blood, to hinder you therefrom; And meet together as exactly as ye can poſſible, at the time appointed, for your faithfull reſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny here in is honourable in the ſight of the Lord, and of his children, who ſuffer bonds, or may ſuffer exilement, or baniſhment, for the ſame Terlin ony: And in ſo doing, ye will be a ſtrength &amp; encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment one to another, and a good ſavour in the hearts of many (that are even ready to joyn with you in the light of the Lord) and a dread to your enemies, for by a fooliſh Nation will he anger the mighty and wiſe men of the Earth, and provoke many people to jealouſie; and the Time is come that whoſoever ſhall call upon the Name of the Lord (in truth) ſhall be ſaved.</p>
            <p>Therefore reſiſt every appearance or thought to the contrary (in the light and ſtrength of God) as a Temptation of the enemy: And remember the Serpent Tempted in <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> to break the Command of the Lord, and is yet neer to betray the Innocer into the ſinners hands, whoſe mercy will be ſound cruelty; for he is not wanting at this day, to ſtrive every way to make you fall from you: ſtedfaſtneſs, neither is his ſubtilty abated, to beguile the ſimple, to draw them into his own ſtate of Condemnation, of which all have been, are, and ever will be partakers, who hearken to his voyce, and obey his Temptation: And this lyes on me to warn you of; For if he get you to bow a little, he will get more ſtrength againſt you, and more hold and ground in you, by his fair flouriſhed baits and cunning crafty allurements, whereby your faith would be weat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and even faile, till he cauſe you to make ſhipwrack there of and of a good Conſcience, through the toſſing your minds to and fro in the Sea of Temptations; and this would be an horrible day of Tempeſts unto you. The Lord my God by his eternal power keep open your underſtandings, that ye may perfectly ſee &amp; diſcern him
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:55272:6"/>in all his wiles and cunning craftineſs, by which he lies in wait to deceive, both within and from without; that ſo ye may be able to reſiſt him in every appearance, and quench all his fiery darts in the living faith, that not a place be given to him, for if ye give him place, he will get more room and matter to work on, till he becomes a ſtrong man armed, to keep the houſe againſt every motion and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of God in you, thereby endeavouring to dwell at peace; but all his ſtrong <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> muſt be ſtormed, and his peice overturned, and the league and covenant with death and hell ſhall be broken, by the pure Life and Seed of God (his head bruiſer) let him do what he can, and then ye will perceive he was a falſe Prophet, and hath deceived you.</p>
            <p>Therefore my dear Friends, watch and pray continually, that ye enter not into temptation, but that ye may ſee every appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of evil and abſtain from it; ſo ſhall the God of Truth and Peace ſanctifie you wholly, in Body, Soul and Spirit, whereby ye ſhall become fit habitations for the Lord to dwell and walk in, and have his Teſtimony in your ſelves, that you are his Children, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taught of him, and preſerved by him to his praiſe, and your ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting comfort and peace. So keep your eye open in the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Light, in which ye will ſee over time, and all things com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in it, and through the end of all temptations, and over all the ſtormes and tempeſts of the wicked, who at this day are like the troubled Sea, and cannot reſt, for there is no peace to the wicked, ſaith my God: But he is your peace and reſting place, who rebukes the Winds, and walkes upon the Sea, and calmes the Stormes at his pleaſure; though in the World ye have Tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Perſecution for his Name ſake, it's but for a moment in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the Eternal Life, if it ſhould be ſo all the days of your Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage on Earth, and but Light Affliction, in compariſon of the exceeding Weight of the Glory ye ſhall be partakers of, as ye abide faithful to the End.</p>
            <p>So the Eternal God of Life and Peace be with you, and preſerve you by his Power, and keep you all valiant for his living Truth, in the pure ſenſe and enjoyment thereof in all your hearts, to the End.</p>
            <p>And my dear Friends, who are in Bonds, Priſons and Holes, for the ſame Teſtimony of Jeſus Chriſt, where ye are oppreſſed and thronged, as ſheep appointed for the ſlaughter, without Mercy from your Adverſaries; be ye not diſcouraged, but lift up your
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:55272:7"/>Heads in the pure Life of your Teſtimony; for this is a day in which the Lord will glorifie himſelf in the eyes of all Nations, and get himſelf a Name above every name, that every knee may bow to him, and that all fleſh may dread and tremble before him, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as the graſs, and as the flower that fadeth away, at the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty and glory of his preſence, who hath touched the Mountains and they ſmoak, and the ſmoak of their torment aſcends night and day, becauſe of the everlaſting burnings, with which he is melting the Hills like wax, and conſuming the ungodly like the fat of Lambs, and folding them up as thornes and ſtubble for the fire. Great is the work which the Lord is doing, and cutting ſhort in righteouſneſs, yea, <hi>ſuch</hi> a <hi>day</hi> is <hi>approaching</hi> as many will not <hi>believe,</hi> though it be, and hath been declared unto them, in which the Lord will <hi>plead</hi> with all fleſh, by <hi>fire</hi> and <hi>ſword,</hi> and with <hi>plague</hi> and <hi>peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, famine</hi> and <hi>earthquakes,</hi> in <hi>divers</hi> places, and <hi>dreadful ſtormes,</hi> and <hi>fearful ſights</hi> within and without, ſo that all fleſh ſhall be pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and wax feeble before him; for the terrors of God (within and without) ſhall ſet themſelves in array againſt the ungodly, and compaſs the wicked as with ſnares of fire, till they are conſumed; and the very ſtars in their courſes ſhall fight againſt them, yea, he will make his wonders known upon them, as in the dayes of <hi>Egypt.</hi> And this I am bold to proclaim, in the Name and Authority of the Everlaſting God, for I have ſeen the conſumption determined, and how it will come to paſs, which is coming upon them as ſwift as on Eagles wings, and it ſhall not tarry nor be prolonged, and he that will come (to reward every man according as his work ſhal be) will come quickly: Bleſſed are they that wait for him.</p>
            <p>Therefor my dear Friends, ſeeing our God is no reſpecter of perſons, but is riſen as a Giant to the Battel, to plead the cauſe of his elect Seed, and to exalt his Name over all the Earth; and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we look for ſuch things, which will certainly come to paſs, and be fulfilled in their ſeaſon (which haſtens) <hi>What manner of perſons ought we to be, in all holy converſation and godlineſs?</hi> and what need have we of diligence, watchfulneſs and readineſs, that we may be found of him in peace, <hi>without ſpot, and blameleſs?</hi> The God of all mercies (whoſe long-ſuffering and kindneſs hath been exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly manifeſted to us-ward) keep you exceeding ſtill, quiet, and low in your minds and ſpirits, fearing to offend him in thought, word and deed, at all times and ſeaſons. And take heed of Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes among your ſelves which are unneceſſary, for the enemy hath
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:55272:7"/>a ſecret end to effect among ſuch things, to draw out your minds from the living ſenſe of the precious tender Seed of God in you, which preſerves the mind joyned to it, in the humbleneſs and watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs againſt every appearance of evil; for he will not let ſlip any opportunity which tends to his advantage, that he may thereby preſerve, continue and uphold, his own Kingdom and Intereſt. Now he perceives his ruine approaching, and his perpetual downfal at hand, who will dwell as long as he can in the two men (one) poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed, but being wholly caſt our from thence, his laſt habitation is the herd of Swine, whom he hath cauſed, and will cauſe, to run down with violence and periſh.</p>
            <p>So my dear Friends, be very careful, and let your words be ſew, and your moderation known unto all men, and in all things, for the Lord is at hand, who weigheth the thoughts, words, and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, intents and purpoſes of all people, with a juſt Ballance, who will not acquit the guilty, without puniſhment, whereſoever it is found. And keep within the bounds of the feeling, of the Seed of God, in all your wayes, for that is the ancient Land-mark, which he that goes beyond tranſgreſſeth; and take heed of loudneſs, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſs, or haſtineſs of ſpeech, in all your diſcourſes about the things of this world (and this I lay upon you from the Lord, to whom you muſt give an account) but be dead &amp; ſlow to ſuch things, and be lively in Chriſt Jeſus the Truth, and yet moderate, patient and cool, for God requireth ſtilneſs, yea, great ſtilneſs, and watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs amongſt you at this day, that you may hear his Voice, and do his Will, and ſtand in his pure Counſel, which the many words with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out knowledge and meekneſs of wiſdom darkeneth, for which the reproofs muſt come. So the Lord guide you in his fear, and gentle peaceable wiſdom, that no folly, ſuperfluity or unſoundneſs, may be found among you, but that ye may all learn of him daily, who is meek and lowly, and be kept in his weighty and ſavoury Life, to the honour of his Name, and the comfort and edification of one another. And mark them that are unruly &amp; walk diſorderly among you, and cauſe diviſions, through their unſubjected wills, and exalt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſpirits, above the Seed of God, which is but one in you all, and have no fellowſhip with them, that they may ſee their ſhame; and yet have no prejudice or enmity riſe in your hearts againſt any, but let your upright Life and Converſation daily judge and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn them, that if poſſible they may be awakened, and be ſenſible of their ſtate, and repent and be ſaved. So let there be no ſtrife or
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:55272:8"/>contentious amongſt you, no needleſs diſputations, whereby the weak may ſtumble, no fooliſh jeſting, no vain jangling, but quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ſoberneſs, with gravity and godlineſs, in all reverence and godly fear, for our God is a conſuming fire; and if the righteous ſcarcely be ſaved, where ſhall the ungodly and tranſgreſſor appear?</p>
            <p>So dear Friends, ſtudy to be quiet, and eat your own bread, and wait for it daily, and be content therewith, and let all your ſtriving be to ſtand ſtill, for herein is your ſtrength encreaſed; and be good examples one unto another, and to all people that may come among you to viſit you, or to behold your order, for the holy Name of our God is greatly concerned in this matter, and we are now the very people by whom he will be honoured and greatly exalted, or elſe reproached and diſhonoured, in this our day and generation. So grieve not the Spirit of God in your ſelves, or others, neither pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke him to jealouſie againſt you, but dwell retired and watchful againſt every motion that would exalt it ſelf above the pretious ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Seed, to hurt it; ſo ſhall ye have peace (as ye dwell in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Mountain) and be juſtified in the ſight of the Lord, and be a good favour in the hearts of all ſober people, whoſe eyes are towards you for good. So mind the honour of God, and bear in remembrance the end for which he hath called you out of the world at this day, to bear your teſtimony in ſufferings for his Name ſake; and be circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, humble, and wiſe in all your wayes, that the Lord may be honoured by you, and his Witneſs anſwered in all People; ſo ſhall his Seed be raiſed, and the weak be ſtrengthened, and your own ſouls comforted in him that guides his Children (that learn of him) in the way of Peace. And for this is the daily travel of my ſoul, who am one in ſufferings with you for the ſame pure teſtimony, which ſhall ſtand for ever.</p>
            <p>And all Friends every where, who have, or may have any occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or buſineſs to any in Authority in the Nations, or who having done any thing in obedience to the Lord (as your faithful Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to his Name) for which ye are, or may be, brought before any of them; or, have any motion lye upon you, to go and warn them, or, any particular of them, concerning the work they are about, or of the day of the Lord, that is coming as a Theife upon them; or as concerning them that <hi>ſuffer bonds,</hi> or the <hi>ſpoiling</hi> of their <hi>goods,</hi> or <hi>ſentence</hi> of <hi>Baniſhment</hi> for the <hi>Truth-ſake,</hi> or the like; this I lay upon you, from the Lord (which hath often riſe in my heart) <hi>go not in your own will, nor time,</hi> but wait upon him in ſtillneſs,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:55272:8"/>and eye his pure preſence and power to go with you, before you, to lead and carry you on in obedience to his own pure motion, in which ye will feel ſtrength ſufficient, and receive the pure wiſdom from above (as in his Light, Dread and Counſel ye abide) ſo to ſpeak, that Gods Witneſs in all may be anſwered, &amp; here ye will be a good ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to him, whether they hear or forbear. So premeditate not afore hand, what to ſpeak, or anſwer, but ſingly give up, and dwell low, and ſubject to the Lord, and keep within the ſeeling of his eternal Power, and ſink into it, and then ye will be preſerved innocent, and cool, and patient, and bold, in dominion over all fear and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which would be ready to enter; and ſo the Truth being kept clear in you, and by you, in all things, the Lord will be honoured, and his Name exalted over all the contary, to whom all honour and fear belongs. And let none ſute or frame themſelves to pleaſe men, but all ſeek to pleaſe the Lord, and ſeek his face, and his glory; and let his Truth be very dear and pretious to you and amongſt you all, yea, more than your own lives, and then by it ye will be preſerved to his praiſe, and your own eternal comfort and peace; for great hath been the ſufferings for its ſake, and many hath ſealed their teſtimony of it with their blood, who have not loved their lives unto death, for the joy that was ſet before them, whoſe faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs lives in an everlaſting record, and can never be blotted out of the hearts of the righteous, but is had in eternal remembrance: the conſideration whereof, ſhall break the hearts of Children that are yet unborn, and the life thereof ſhall raiſe up thouſands from the dead, who ſhall give glory to God in their behalf. So in his Truth, the Lord God of all mercies and everlaſting bleſſings keep you all. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In whoſe bleſſed Will, I lye down, with all the faithful and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right in heart, dayly waiting in his pure Light (which makes all things manifeſt) to know more of his counſel, and to be obedient thereunto, in whatſoever he requireth of me; in which I exhort ſome, that they ſuffer not a motion of that ſpirit of <hi>Core</hi> or <hi>Eliab</hi> to riſe in their hearts, leſt thereby they endanger themſelves; for what was <hi>Moſes?</hi> and what was <hi>Aaron?</hi> and what are all that bare a pure Teſtimony this day, for the Name of the Moſt Holy dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful God, but ſuch as hazard their Lives, and are your ſervants for Chriſts ſake? therefore let ſuch be very careful, and tender in this matter; for cannot we ſay to them (as little to <hi>David</hi> his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) <hi>Is there not a cauſe?</hi> Do not the care and zeal for the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:55272:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the great and holy Name of our God dayly increaſe in our hearts? I Can truly ſay, <hi>The zeal of thine houſe hath even eaten me up.</hi> That his living Truth and People may be kept blameleſs, and ſpotleſs, in this great and notable day of Tryal, is the travel of my breathing ſoul, day and night; and I ſeek not mine own honour, but the honour of him that hath had mercy upon me, who hath opened mine eyes, and given me of his free Spirit, &amp; eternal Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, and all I have, I have received from him, and I have nothing to boaſt of, but in the Lord, and his Mercies, which endureth for ever, in whoſe Salvation I rejoyce, and in his fear I delight: and Lord let me never forget thy <hi>Name,</hi> nor the multitude of thy Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyes toward me, and toward all thy People, but let me ever give thanks to thee in the lively remembrance of them, who is ſetting a Remnant as watchmen upon the walls of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> who can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not hold their peace, for her ſake, day nor night, till ſhe is made the Praiſe of the whole Earth, and ſo much the more as they ſee the day approaching, though their life is in great ſtillneſs; and I could be content to be ſilent, but I muſt obey his requirings, or I cannot be clear in his ſight; And I know to this end hath he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved me to this day and hour, in the ſecret of his Pavilion; bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be his Name for ever.</p>
            <p>Into whoſe hand I freely commit my ſoul, and body, and all that he hath given me, and all his dear people every where, to be diſpoſed at his good will and pleaſure, in which I feele my reward with me, and my witneſs is in heaven, and the true joy of the Lord is in my heart as an open fountain, which none knows but the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed from the earch; and yet I am dayly a man of ſorrowes, and well acquainted with griefs, for the redemption of his ſeed in Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity, and for the whole Creation, that groaneth under the bondage of corruption; but in all eſtates I have learned to be content, knowing the Lord is with me, and hears, and in due time will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the breathings of his own, to whom be the glory, dominion and praiſes, now and for evermore. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>I am your dear Brother and Companion, who ſuffer with patience for the everlaſting Truth of God (which muſt ſpread over all the Earth, and be eſtabliſhed on the top of all Mountains) in which I bid you, Farewel.</hi> W. B.</signed>
               <dateline>From <hi>Hertford,</hi> where I remain a Priſoner for the Teſtimony of Jeſus Chriſt, <date>the 26 of the 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Month. 1664.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
